So, today I'm going to review the Croove
coffee sifter. Now, I've used this
before. A few of you have asked me to
review it, having seen it in some of the
videos I've done where I compare two
different grinders and the kind of
quality of grind coming from them. And
so today, I'm going to dive into this
and tell you what I
think. Crew sent me the nicest set that
they offer, which is very kind of them.
Uh, you get 12 different sized saves
that go inside this thing. And this
thing has three trays that holds two
different civ sizes. Here's the theory.
If you have a broad range of particle
sizes, when you brew a cup of coffee,
that's bad. because the very fine pieces
will give up their flavor very quickly
and begin to over extract and add quite
a lot of bitterness and then the very
large pieces won't extract properly and
they'll end up making the cup a little
bit sour. Obviously, anything in the
middle should brew ideally pretty
normally. But what you'll get is some
tasty coffee, some bitter coffee, and
some sour coffee all in one cup. That's
not ideal. And so here you're supposed
to add in two saves. One to screen out
the largest size and one to screen out
the finest size. Now, because different
brew methods require different grind
sizes, that's why you've got a bunch of
different sibs. Now, one quick thing. I
actually think it's a little bit
simplistic to talk about coffee as if
it's two-dimensional. Particle sizes are
three-dimensional. It's really about
surface area as much as it's about
particle size. You could have a
perfectly round particle and you could
have a long skinny particle that in
theory would fit through the same sieve.
In addition, I think it's also a little
bit complicated to say all fines are bad
and should be avoided and they don't
contribute positive things to cups of
coffee. But when we dive into this, it's
really about who are you and what do you
need from this? Now, they do a set that
starts at $50 with just two sibs and
then it runs all the way up to about
$130 for this set. If you're using a
pretty cheap grinder, be that a pretty
cheap electric grinder, uh be it a blade
grinder, like a worly blade grinder, if
you're using a cheap hand grinder, then
to be honest, this probably isn't a good
solution for you. In truth, you're
better spending $130 on a better coffee
grinder. Putting coffee from a a cheap
hand grinder into this will mean that
you screen out quite a lot of particles
and it means you have to put in a lot of
ground coffee to get enough of the good
stuff out to get a brew. It can nearly
double the cost of the coffee you're
using due to the amount that you're
throwing away. And so for my money, not
a great investment. Uh spend more on
your grinder. Now things change a little
bit when you get to the mid-range to the
high-end grinders to get a traditional
set of saves. Most people use ones made
by a company called Endicott. Now, a
single civ from Endicott may be between
$50 to $100 secondhand on eBay. They are
expensive. So, a full set of saves like
this could run in excess of $1,000. So,
in comparison, $130 is incredibly cheap.
If you want to start messing around with
particle size, this is a pretty great
way to go. I used it at home for a
little while and then eventually I
brought it into work because it's square
mile. It's much more interesting as a an
experimental area for others to play
around with different stuff. But for me,
for my dayto-day with a decent grinder,
a decent brewer, I didn't feel there was
a significant bump in quality that
yielded adding time, work, and
additional cost through wastage to my
morning cup of coffee. If I was
competing in a brewer competition, would
I want to experiment with this? I might.
Their recommendation for pourover coffee
is to use a 400 micron and an 800 micron
sie. For me, that actually gives a
pretty wide range of particle sizes,
some will be literally twice the size of
others. And so, while it might be a good
way for me to be uh communicating with a
friend about how I'm brewing and the
kind of grind size I'm using, it's far
from perfect for that.
However, if you're a coffee professional
and you want to start experimenting with
siving with different grind sizes with
the effect of uniformity on brewing,
this is a much much much cheaper option
than going down the route of scientific
saves. That isn't to say that this thing
is perfect. There are a couple of things
about this that frustrate me a little
bit. Two main things. one, the way that
this fits together, it just feels a
little bit loose and it slips apart
quite
easily. Secondly, and probably my
biggest frustration is that to change a
civ is a little bit fussy as work goes.
Each of the saves have a little rubber
gasket on them that hold them in place.
But when you're changing a civ, it can
be quite frustrating to pop in all three
sides of that triangle and get them
locked in properly. And it's easy
actually to have them be unlocked by
mistake. And obviously any coffee can
just sneak around the side of that. So I
wish that it was a little bit easier to
change the filters sometimes. I have a
little bit of frustration there. Some
sizes are easier than others, which is
kind of down to the flexibility of the
mesh
itself. I haven't been able to test the
validity of the sizings. Now, I don't
have a set of saves here anymore to
compare this to to see if it screens out
the same amount of 300 micron particles
as an Endicott test civ would do.
However, I do think it's pretty useful.
It's pretty easy to use. I think it's
pretty inexpensive. And I think that if
you want to start exploring coffee a
little bit more, this is for you. If you
want to make your cup of coffee a little
bit better in the mornings, I'd probably
just invest in a better grinder. Means
less wastage. It means less work, less
time between you waking up and the first
coffee of the day. So overall,
interesting professionally, but I'm not
sure I'd recommend it for the average
home user.
I hope you enjoyed the video. One more
quick thing, there are t-shirts. So,
this is the Gym 7 t-shirt. This is the
cover of the book that's coming out. The
ebook's now live and available. And
people asked for some t-shirts, so we
made some t-shirts. They're available in
lots of different colors. If you want
one, I'll leave a link in the
description down below. As always, your
feedback is welcome. I want to hear what
you think. I want to know what you want
me to review next. Feedback, comments,
questions. If you like it, give it a
like. Thank you so much for watching.
Have a great day.